RESEARCH SOFTWARE ENGINEER

DIANA MARIA TORRES RICAURTE

DOCTOR IN ENGINEERING



dimatori@gmail.com dimtorresri@unal.edu.co





OBJECTIVE

I want to apply in research my knowledge and experience in the areas of software engineering and quality. I have a special interest in designing, developing and executing software solutions that drive the advancement in research across various disciplines. I am excited to collaborate closely with researchers, propose feasible software products that align with their requirements and enable efficient access to their research data.

My enthusiasm for continuous learning, my commitment to excellence, and desire to make a positive impact on society form the cornerstone of my professional approach.

SOFT SKILLS

- Analytical skills with the ability to adopt strategies and quickly integrate new knowledge
- Ability to work independently
- Effective problem-solving capabilities
- Goal-oriented and driven to achieve results
- Skilled in knowledge transfer and effective communication

HARD SKILLS

- Software development and maintain best practices
- Programming languages (Python, C++, Java, Visual, Scheme, MoZart)
- Web development (HTML, JavaScript, CSS, Php, ReactJS)
- DBMS (SQL, Postgres, MySQL)
- Version control system (Git, GitHub)
- Operating systems (Windows, MS-DOS, Linux)

EXPERIENCE

Python software developer | Jul 2022 - Sep 2022

Private project

 Software development to normalize large data file with address information. This project was integrated with a geocoder.

University Professor | Aug 2021 - Dec 2021 Institución Universitaria ITM

Courses:

- Introduction to data science course in Python
- Software development course
- General systems theory course

EDUCATION

Doctorate in Engineering – Systems and Informatics | 2019

Universidad Nacional de Colombia

Master of Engineering - Systems Engineering 2014

Universidad Nacional de Colombia

Bachelor of Systems Engineering | 2003

Universidad del Valle

RESEARCH SOFTWARE ENGINEER DIANA MARIA TORRES RICAURTE

QUALIFICATIONS

- React.js | 2023
- NPM: Package and dependency management in JavaScript | 2023
- Frontend Developer | 2023
- Python: Comprehensions, Functions and Error Handling | 2023

PUBLICATIONS

Towards a theory of interoperability of software systems | 2023

Ingeniería e Investigación Journal DOI:

https://doi.org/10.15446/ing.investig.102248

Representing Interoperability between Software Systems by using Pre-conceptual Schemas | 2022

International Journal on Electrical Engineering and Informatics

DOI: https://doi.org/10.15676/ijeei.2022.14.1.7

Towards a terminology unification in software interoperability | 2018

44th Euromicro Conference on Software Engineering and Advanced Applications (SEAA), Czech

DOI: https://doi.org/10.1109/SEAA.2018.00083

See more publications on **ORCiD**

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Member of the Research Group on Computational Languages | Since 2008

Projects:

- Formulating a theory about interoperability among heterogeneous software systems, based on the Semat kernel
- A method for measuring software test team productivity

Member of the Research Group on Visual Environments of Applied Programming AVISPA | 2000 – 2003

Projects:

- CRE2: application for reconfiguring a power distribution network
- Loss reduction in distribution networks using concurrent constraint programming
- PATHOS: Object Oriented concurrent constraint timetabling for real world cases

LIFE INTERESTS

- Spend time with my family
- Travel and visit new places
- Practice tennis
- Improve my English
- Try new food
- Read literature